Finding Aid for Lee Raymond Dice papers, 1903-1964
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Lee Raymond Dice papers 1903-1964
Dice, Lee Raymond, 1887-1977.
6 linear feet
851106 Aa 2
Professor of zoology, and director of the Institute of Human Biology. Administrative files of the Institute, professional correspondence, journals and field notebooks, including observations of Alaska, 1911-1912, and autobiographical and family material; and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Professor Dice (donor no. 3454 ).
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The collection is open to research.
Lee Raymond Dice was born July 15, 1887, in Savannah, Georgia. He graduated from Washington State College Preparatory School in 1907, received his B.A. from Stanford University in 1911 and his M.S. (1914) and Ph.D. (1915) from the University of California.
Before coming to the University of Michigan in 1919, Dice taught zoology at Kansas State College, was a zoologist at Kansas Agricultural Experimental Station, was assistant professor of biology at the University of Montana, and assistant in zoology at the University of Illinois.
He began at the University of Michigan as curator of mammals in the Museum of Zoology and instructor in zoology. He was promoted to assistant professor in 1928, associate professor in 1934, and full professor in 1943. In 1927, he had also become research associate in the Laboratory of Mammalian Genetics, later director of the Vertebrate Genetics Laboratory in 1934, and director of the Institute of Human Biology in 1950. In 1942, he founded the U-M Medical Center's Heredity Clinic.
Dice was a member of the American Association for the Advancement of Science; American Society of Mammalogist (Vice-President 1947-51); Nature Conservancy (President 1948); American Society of Human Genetics (President 1950-1951); Ecological Society of America (President 1936-37); Society of Systematic Zoology (President 1949-50); Society for the Study of Evolution (Vice-President 1947-48, 1953-54); American Eugenics Society; British Ecological Society; Genetics Society of America; American Society of Naturalists; Society of Vertebrate Paleontologists; Member of the Board of Trustees of Cranbrook Institute of Science and of the Advisory Committee of the animal Welfare Institute.
He was the author of numerous scientific papers and of three books: Biotic provinces of North America; National Communities; and Man's nature and nature's man-the ecology of human communities.
He died January 31, 1977.
The Dice collection consists of administrative files of the Institute of Human Biology, professional correspondence, journals and field notebooks, including observations of Alaska, 1911-1912, and autobiographical and family material, and photographs. The papers are organized of the following series: Professional Correspondence; Institute of Human Biology; University of Michigan Other; and Personal and miscellaneous.
Subjects:
Alaska.; Dice, Lee Raymond, 1887-1977.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Zoology.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Institute of Human Biology.; Zoology.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Alaska.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Professional Correspondence, 1933-1964
  - 1933-1956
    - A-D (Box 1)
    - E-H (Box 2)
    - I-P (Box 3)
    - Q-Z (Box 4)
  - 1956-1964
    - A-E (Box 4)
    - F-Z (Box 5)
- Institute of Human Biology
  - Staff meetings, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Annual reports (Box 5)
  - Ad hoc Committee on the Institute of Human Biology (Box 5)
  - Descriptive material (Box 5)
  - Administrative reports regarding objectives and needs of IHB (Box 5)
  - Administrative notebook (Box 5)
  - Phoenix Project research proposal (Box 5)
  - Rockefeller Foundation research proposal (Box 5)
  - Systematic Biology editorial board (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
- University of Michigan Other
  - Division of Biological Sciences (Box 5)
  - Laboratory of Vertebrate Biology, meeting minutes, 1939-1952, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Administrative units
    - A-Z (Box 6)
- Personal and miscellaneous
  - National Communities book: reviewer's comments and LRD response (Box 6)
  - Personal material: include appointments, bibliography, and family reports (Box 6)
  - "Interior Alaska in 1911 and 1912 Observations by a Naturalist" with accompanying photographs, 1911-1912, 1 volume and 8 envelopes in 1 folder; (photocopies (Box 6)
  - Memoir and family papers, (photocopy (Box 6)
  - Journals and field notebooks, 1903-1918, 2 expandable folders (Box 6)
    (include notes on Alaska, Montana, California, Kansas, and Washington)
  - Reprints of writings (Box 6)
    (include bibliography of Dice's publications)